Venkata Matcha

7579942295 | mvs.teja91@gmail.com

Professional Summary

Senior Software Engineer with over 8 years of industrial experience and a Master's degree in Computer Science from Old Dominion University, I have a proven track record of developing complex software applications that meet industry standards. I stay up-to-date with the latest design trends and best practices by exploring web.dev, dev.to and Dribble communities.

Technical Skills

Programming Languages: JavaScript, Java, SQL, Typescript

Web Technologies: HTML, CSS, ReactJS, Angular 2, Node.js, Jest, Enzyme, Ember Js. UI Framework: Redux, Fluent UI, Material UI, Bootstrap, Highcharts, Plotly.

Backend Framework: SpringBoot, Express.

Cloud Services: AWS, Google Cloud Platform

Automation Tools: Docker, Kubernetes, Shell scripting, Jenkins

Database Technologies: MySQL, MongoDB, Oracle.

Search and Analytics: ElasticSearch, GCP.

Data Querying: Axios, QueryDSL, React Query

Task management:
Application Monitoring:
Design:
Version Control:
Agile Methodologies:
Confluence, JIRA.
New Relic, Sentry
Figma, Invision.
Git, Bitbucket, Gitlab
Scrum, Kanban

Experience

Graduate Research Assistant

Old Dominion University

Aug 2021 - May 2023

Norfolk, VA

- Built end-to-end systems for ODU websites, with Front-end in Angular and React, And Backend in Node's Express JS, MySql.
- Solved the recurring dates problem in a room booking Web Interface system, ensuring seamless functionality.
- Implemented ElasticSearch for importing and managing large datasets, incorporating two-factor authentication and password reset via email.
- Developed Real-Time communication application use cases such as Order updates, Chat messaging.
- Created a reusable component library for the web application using Angular Material, resulting in faster development time for new features.
- Implemented an efficient data fetching layer using Node.js, Express.js, and React-query.
- Incorporated third-party APIs, such as a payment gateway(Square) into the website, allowing for secure online payments, into the web application for data exchange and real-time updates.

Tech Stack - Angular 2, TypeScript, NodeJS, Express, Socket IO, MySQL, AWS EC2, Gitlab, Shell scripting, Square SDK.

Software Engineer Intern

Jun 2022 - Aug 2022

Chesapeake, VA

Map Communications Inc.

- Developed end-to-end web and mobile systems for a Virtual Receptionist software company.
- Implemented document sharing and metrics dashboard features, improving overall productivity.
- Increased efficiency of Employee management portal by refactoring complex database structures and queries in MySQL helped in reducing response time from 45 seconds to 700 milliseconds
- Refactored and converted UI projects into reusable components, optimizing bandwidth usage and enhancing site performance.
- Managed CI/CD pipelines, and implemented build scripts, continuous integration infrastructure, and deployment tools.
- Worked extensively with Restful APIs, implementing JWT and LDAP authentication and handling bulk operations, using packages like QueryDSL.

- Form Validations and Handling Dynamic Validations for Form using Yup.
- Utilized CSS-in-JS techniques to create a consistent and visually appealing UI.
- Ensured authentication and authorization using JWT tokens.
- Leveraged modern JavaScript features such as async/await and Promises for asynchronous coding.
- Conducted pre-testing of web service calls using Swagger UI and Postman.

Tech Stack - Linux, Gitlab, Jenkins, Shell scripting, React, Material UI, React Native, nginx, Java, SpringBoot, Oracle DB, React query, CI/CD GitLab, Oracle

Senior Software Engineer

Nov 2018 - Aug 2021

Freshworks

Chennai, India

- Successfully developed and migrated data visualizations from Plotly to Highcharts.
- Implemented complex UI features such as bulk updates, bulk email, and consumption of form services.
- Participated in code reviews on Github to ensure code quality and adherence to best practices.
- Followed SDLC phases such as ideation, planning, development, testing, and production deployment. All phases were executed in an Agile 2-week sprint model.
- Collaborated with teams to slice epics into actionable user stories and resolve inter-team dependencies.
- Collaborated with peers from development, product, and project management teams to identify blockers in grooming sessions and reduce sprint planning time.
- Received mockups on Figma, Understood user flows, and developed UI based on the wireframes.
- Wrote tests using Jest and Enzyme, resulting in 80% code coverage. This ensured the reliability and correctness of the application.
- Defined test cases and metrics in collaboration with QA.
- Consumed RESTful services developed in Java.
- Worked with CI/CD pipelines in Jenkins, and deployed packages and assets to AWS and Kubernetes clusters through kubectl services.
- Optimized website performance using tools like Lighthouse and resolved front-end-related issues.
- Redesigned scroll behavior using intersection observer API and other proofs-of-concept, resulting in 30% less page loading time.
- Architected Freshworks CRM Outlook Add-in using React.

Tech Stack - React, Redux, Typescript, Highcharts, LocalForage, Plotly, Fluent UI, Ember JS, Jest, Enzyme, Highcharts, Kubernetes, Java, Spring, AWS - EC2, S3., Github, JIRA, New Relic.

Senior Associate Aug 2013 - Nov 2018

Cognizant technology solutions

Chennai, India

- Implemented a MySQL database to manage user data, admin data, question banks, and past scores
- Built frontend with functionalities such as registration, take quiz, admin access, managing questions, and managing candidates, styled the application in Pearson's DLS (Design Language System).
- The UX team uploaded mockups on Invision, UI based on the feedback given by me.
- Set up route-based code-splitting of application code. Worked on improving the landing page's load speed, Reducing the time to first interactive by 30%.
- Responsible for gathering business and functional requirements (Requirement Analysis Documents), and designing and developing web applications.
- Implemented Jest snapshot and unit testing, integrating pre-commit scripts.
- Worked in Agile sprint model.

Tech Stack - React, Redux Thunk, Redux Form, Pearson components(CSS framework), Jest, Enzyme, AngularJS, Bootstrap, On-prem Debian, Invision, Confluence, Bitbucket.

Education

Master of Science (M.S.) - Computer Science

Old Dominion University, cum laude

Aug 2021 - May 2023

Norfolk, VA

Bachelor of Engineering (B.E.) - Electronics Engineering

Indian Institute of Information Technology

Sep 2008 - May 2012 Chennai, India.